Never forget why you are the church.
I want you to go ahead and turn your Bibles
to Revelation, chapter 8,
Revelation chapter 8.
All right, if you're happy, Lord, say amen.
Amen, amen.
I tell you, you know, we have worship nights here,
and we actually, we've been talking about scheduling our next worship
night, so we got to get that done, but we also,
I was contacted by a church in
Alexandria, 1st Baptist Alexandria,
pastored by Elijah Burns, who,
that's the one that took my reign as the youngest lead
pastor in middle Tennessee, if not Tennessee in general.
And so he was like,
Hey, man, I want to do a worship night, and I want to get a bunch of churches together.
Will you make sure the worship part is good.
And I said, absolutely.
So if you are interested, you can go ahead and put this down.
September 20th, that evening, I
believe starting at 6th will be in Alexandria, 1st Baptist Church.
Alexandria.
is gonna be, it's not, it's not a youth event.
It's just a worship night.
And so from what I understand, it's one of the 1st that they've done in that area.
So, uh, the church that we are hosting it at, I
think, instead about 200.
we're hoping we're hoping to have standing room only.
And it's going to be a great time.
So if you want to worship with us there, you
can absolutely come and join us.
Okay?
We continue to look at the 7 trumpets
of judgment, found in Revelation 8.
Two weeks ago, we went over the
1st 3 trumpets, and so we're going to dive right in the text.
And before we do that, I do want to say, it is awesome that
we have men of God that can fill in the pulpit when I'm not here.
And so, again, I just want to say, I know on Wednesdays,
especially, it seems like it's been multiple times to
where I know that I know Richard's done it, Mark's done it, Law's done it.
And that's not the only talented men we have, but those are the
men that stood in the gap at that time.
So, uh, if you miss that and you would like
to see them and hear them, uh, it is on our media players.
So I went back and watched them and stuff.
And so I think Richard's your favorite because he was the shortest.
Actually, no, Mark is your favorite because he was the shortest.
I think Mark was like 6.5 minutes.
It was a great, it was a great time.
Yeah.
No, I'm kidding.
But anytime you do something like that first.
I know my 1st one, I really, really,
man, it's like you have all your planning.
You have your notes out there.
You're ready for a 30 minute in your head message and,
uh, you know, you just, you just talk it a lot faster and you think.
it's been, it's been really cool to see something that hasn't
always been, if that makes sense, to be able to comfortably
not be here in those moments and know that the church is getting fed.
So I just want to praise God for that.
So anyway, we're gonna look at Revelation 8, verse 7 through 11.
It says this.
The 1st angel sounded, and they followed hell
and fire and mingled with blood, and they were cast upon the earth.
And the 3rd part of trees were burnt up and all
green grass was burnt up.
And the 2nd angels sounded, and it was as were a great
mountain burning with fire was cast into the sea, and a
3rd part of the sea became blood.
And the 3rd part of the creatures, which were in the sea, it had life
died in the 3rd part of the ships were destroyed.
And the 3rd angel sounded, and there fell a great star from heaven,
burning as it were a lamp, and it fell upon the 3rd
part of the rivers and upon the fountains of waters.
And the name of the star is called wormwood, and the 3rd
part of the waters became wormwood.
And many died.
Many men died of the waters because they were made bitter.
So here's where we are at in the end time great tribulation judgment.
A terrible weather storm, including fire, hail, and
blood has occurred, taking out a 3rd of the trees and burning
up all the graphs, something like a mountain has hit
the sea, turning a 3rd of the oceans and seas in the blood.
With this a 3rd of the sea, life has died and a 3rd of the ships were destroyed.
Then we see a great star, which we can speculate, could
be some meteoric event, fall into the rivers and fresh
water sources.
This makes them bitter, and we see that many men die because of it.
And church, we are just 3 trumpets in to seven.
Now, you might be thinking, man, this is this is not fun to talk
about, and I understand, and it's really not fun to read either or really preach about.
But can I tell you something?
God takes sin serious.
And this world has been cursed by sin
ever since the Garden of Eden.
And this is how God makes everything you, he destroys
to make new.
And so there is no possible way that we can even imagine how
bad the great tribulation is going to be for those who are
here on earth during that time.
So we continue the title.
God's wrath announced and active.
Let's pray.
Father, we thank you, Lord, for this night.
We thank you for your word.
And God, even though this is a difficult text to preach
and to hear, God, I pray that you give us wisdom and discernments tonight with it.
We thank you, we love you, since Jesus name, we pray.
Amen.
We're going to look right at the 4th trumpet in verses 12 through 13.
It says this, and the 4th angel sounded, and
the 3rd part of the sun was smitten, and the 3rd part of the moon, and a
3rd part of the stars.
So as the 3rd part of them was darkened, and the day shone not
for a 3rd part of it, and a night likewise.
And I beheld and heard an angel flying through the midst of heaven, saying
with a loud voice, whoa, whoa, whoa, to the inhabitors
of the earth by reason of the other voices of the trumpets of
the 3 angels, which are yet to sound.
Now we see here that God's judgment now
enters into the heavens.
A 3rd of the sun, the
moon, and the stars all get struck and turn dark.
This makes a 3rd of the day and night without any
light at all.
Now, some of you might say, well, what are you talking about light at nighttime?
If you've ever seen a full moon, you understand that it kind
of, you know, gives light, right?
It's not pitch dark, but there's some moonlight.
As a matter of fact, there was a time, and this was really
dumb, but we were hanging out with
some guys at mom and dad's house, and it was like, I
don't know, I might have been 1130, 12 o'clock or whatever.
And so, you know, when you hang out with Christian friends, you don't drink or
do drugs or anything like that, you just do other stupid things.
So we were gonna, we said, you know what, we can't see nothing.
So we're going to go play some football.
And we get into the field.
I mean, you can't see really much of anything.
And, I mean, you can see, but you can't see.
You know what I'm saying?
And, uh, man, I'll never forget.
So I was on Isaiah's team.
Isaiah's over here.
He's hopefully remembering the story.
But I was on Isaiah's team, and man, I'm going, and I hit a slant
around everything, and I put my hands up, and all I see is this right here.
And then all of a sudden, boom, I'm talking about that football smacks
me square in my nose.
But listen, what I'm trying to say is it's not smart to
play football at nighttime when you can't see, amen?
But right here is gonna be no light for a 3rd of the night,
no light for the 3rd of the day.
This is going to make proms that we don't even see coming.
This creates a global phenomenon of unnatural darkness.
To look at this from a practical standpoint, if
the earth had not been drastically affected already enough, this
unnatural darkness impacts the environment as well.
Reduce the sunlight by a 3rd and you hinder plant growth.
That is one of the realities of already
of less trees and grass and bitter water, but food production
becomes almost impossible at this point.
The natural cycles are once again negatively impacted.
Winter becomes an ongoing danger for many parts of
the planet.
It is interesting that there have been movies and TV shows
that have attempted and showing the devastation of
something like this, but it's just movie.
just cinema.
When it really happens, it's going to be way worse than we could ever imagine.
Now, this is when we come to an interesting part of
these trumpet announcements.
If you look at verse 13, it says this.
And I beheld and heard an angel flying through
the midst of heaven, saying with a loud voice, woe,
woe, woe, to the inhabitants of the earth, by reason
of the other voices of the trumpet, of the 3 angels which are yet to sound.
Now, I wanted to connect this to here because just of time's
sake, but I want to nerd out for a 2nd because I
think that, and I hope that we enjoy the deeper topics
and concepts in the Bible that if not taken carefully,
we will read right through.
As a matter of fact, I'm with another brother, I am
reading one chapter a day and we text each other
kind of what, you know, God has shown us in that chapter,
and it's amazing because I've read the Bible all the way through.
I've, you know, we're in Acts right now.
I've read Acts, I mean, dozens and dozens of times all the way through.
And it doesn't matter how many times, every
single time I read it.
It's not that I get something new because I know that it's
been there, but it's new to me, right?
God shows me something that I had not realized
before.
And so I think what we turned into in a modern
church, and listen, I know we don't all have time just to sit around like the,
you know, like the Pharisees and sit in the worship center and
have our Bible out and just kind of nitpick everything.
But man, sometimes it's good just to take your time.
We get so caught up in these plans to
read the Bible in 6 months or this or that or devotions.
Man, sometimes it's good just to really sit with God's word and
to see the deeper things.
There's too many resources for us to be ignorant of scripture.
I mean, there's just too many resources.
I mean, listen, you don't have to go to seminary to be able to go to seminary anymore.
You know what I'm saying?
I mean, you can you may not get the degree that comes with it,
but you'll get the knowledge.
And let me just tell you something.
The knowledge is way better than a degree.
I've got a degree in my office right now, concrete industry management.
I done nothing with it.
I got the degree.
I got the piece of paper.
It doesn't matter anything to my life.
You understand what I'm saying?
But when we learn about God and his word, it does matter to our life.
So bear with me here.
When reading verse 13, you have an angel flying through the midst declaring the woes.
Interestingly, if you look at other translations,
you will find being an eagle, it being
an eagle announcing it rather than an angel.
It is almost certain that the original Greek text used
the term eagle rather than angel.
Now, why did they change it?
Well, 1st off, it really has, I just want to say it really has no significant
impact on the message itself.
In other words, this is not a salvation issue.
I want you to know something.
Most of revelation is not a salvation issue.
Right?
He is the door.
Amen.
And you can only get to heaven through him.
But all, you know, whether we see it this way or that way,
literal symbolic, this is not, we can disagree
and still go to heaven together.
Does that make sense?
But that doesn't mean that we just, you know, skip it
and say, who cares because it's here and God gave it to us.
But it could be as simple as the scribes changed it
to angel because it's seen more appropriate than eagle.
It's seeing more, you know, we're talking about angels the entire time,
declaring a trumpet judgment.
So obviously it should have said, angel.
However, the original term used in the Greek literally
means eagle or could also mean vulture.
Now, what's cool about this.
And regardless of what it actually means, it's cool to look at this,
the Greek word atos carries some interpretive flexibility.
It can mean either eagle or vulture, each carrying
different symbolic weight.
If eagle is correct, the emphasis falls on the bird's strength and swiftness.
serving as a powerful proclaimer while imparting a sense of trepidation
to its nature as a fierce predator.
Alternatively, a vulture is the intended meaning.
The imagery becomes one of doom and destruction as vultures
hovering over a decaying carcass signal and pending devastation.
I got that from the Bible commentary, reddish Bible commentary.
Now, the reason this is good to bring up is because the
Bible reaches to such depth, the normal reader will
never even dip their toe in two.
So as we grow in our faith, we ought to enjoy going deeper.
The deeper we go into God's Word, the more wisdom and understanding we will have.
Now this isn't just for Bible trivia, but
for our walk with Christ as well.
The overall point of this messenger, whether an eagle,
vulture, or angel is the next 3 trumpets are going
to be even worse than the 1st four.
Now.
You might be thinking, why in the world would you nerd out on that?
Well, for some reason, as I am preparing
this message, okay, and I'm typing all my stuff in,
God just puts on my heart, a good time,
since we talk about how some translations say this, some
translations say that, to talk about Bible translations.
And so we're going to take a little bit of a commercial here, and we're going to get back
to the 4th trumpet and talk about what it could be and what it couldn't be.
But too often, Bible translations are brought to a level of
importance that I think does more damage than good.
I'm not saying that Bible translations aren't important.
It does matter which translation you use.
There are good ones and there are bad ones.
They're ones that call themselves translations that are not Bible translations, right?
And so what we sit here and, you
know, we have a lot of people and you can be yourself a KJV
only, all you want.
I think the KJV is a great translation.
But it's not the only great translation.
As a matter of fact, the KJV uses the what's
called the Mesoretic text for the Old Testament, and
the text is receptive for the New Testament.
This is not a bad thing, however, over
time, there have been older manuscripts discovered
and used for other translations.
Other translations like the ESV, the NIV, the
NSB 95, and even CSB, use the older manuscripts,
like the Dead Sea Scrolls, the Alexandrian, the Codex
synaticists in addition to the newer ones.
And you might say, what in the world, why are you saying this?
Because I think it is important for us to understand.
I was speaking to a pastor, friend, about Bible
translations, and I told him that I really was getting into the NSB
95, and I did my studying, and I enjoyed
that translation.
And it's really the most readable word by word translation there is.
And I know we can probably argue about that, but that's, you
know, someone has to be wrong and it's just not me.
especially the 1995 publication of it.
And uh, But he told me this, and this is
what kind of, this is, this is kind of the point that I'm making.
I said, man, hey, you know what?
I mean, at that point in my pastoring,
man, I didn't dare use any other translation in KJV in my preaching.
I didn't dare.
Not even you, King James version.
It's just like, man, that's just that's just not going to work.
It's going to be voted out and it's going to get me, you know, beat
up in a parking lot, it's just not going to be good.
But I told her, I said, man, it would be really cool if I could, you know, share different
scriptures because I study out of this Bible.
And he told me that if he had ever changed his translation, it would destroy
the faith of his congregation.
Now that's a strong statement there.
Obviously, this is a KJV only church that we're talking about here.
My friends' church.
But in reality, he's probably right.
However, this is where we're missing the point.
So we're going to do an exercise tonight.
Are y'all ready to do an exercise?
You don't have to get up.
You don't have to, you know, move anything.
just, I want you to just sit there for a second.
You ready?
You ready for success?
One of the foundational scriptures of the gospel is John 316, amen?
Say amen to that.
John 316 says this, for gods to love the world, that
he here has only begotten son, that whosoever believes in him should not
perish, but have everlasting life.
Amen.
Isn't that awesome?
That was the KJV.
The new King James version says this.
John 316, for God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son and whoever believeth in him.
believes in him, should not perish, but have everlasting life.
Amen.
isn't that beautiful?
The end is 95, John 316 says this.
For God so loved the world that he gave his only begotten son, that
whoever believes in.
I keep on trying to do the KJV version.
That's that's a Wana for me back in the day.
Then whoever believes in him shall not perish, but have eternal life.
Is that good?
Amen?
Y'all not, listen, 1st off, if
nothing else, we're reading John 316 over and over again, this is good stuff, okay?
This is good preaching right here.
All right?
Okay, ESV, John 316.
You ready?
For God to love the world, that he gave his only son that whoever believes
in him should not perish, but have eternal life.
Is that not good?
NIV, John 316, for God so love the world that he gave his
only his one and only son that whoever believes in him shall
not perish, but have eternal life.
John 316, CSB, for God to love the world in this way.
He gave his one and only sons, so everyone who believes in him
shall not perish, or will not perish, but have eternal life.
Amen.
I'm going to give you another one real quick.
The ASV.
No one uses that anymore.
That used to be the textbook for auto seminary.
That's an old translation.
John 316, for God so loved the world that he gave, his only begotten
son, that whosoever believeth on him should not perish, but have
eternal life, someone say, amen.
Now listen.
I just read to you 7 different translations.
Of what I would say is one of the top most
important should be used in every evangelical
situation, soul winning encounter there is.
And out of 7 translation of the same scripture,
We can learn and share the same truth.
What is that truth?
God loves me.
God sent his son from me.
I don't have to perish.
If I believe in him, I'll have eternal life.
Is that good?
Man, God just spoke to me with that this morning.
And now listen, do not hear what I'm not saying.
Again, not every translation is created equal, not every translation is the word of God.
I will go ahead and tell you that.
There's this passion translation and I know that, you
know, everyone's heard the perverted, the
corrupted, just carnal, queen,
queen, James, whatever translation or whatever.
I mean, there's there's some evil stuff that have people have done with God's word.
It disgusting.
But I can tell you that there are many translations that are good translations.
Now, you say, what is the best translation?
I'm going to give you an answer that just about every good
Bible teacher should say.
The best translation is the one you'll read.
Hey, man.
Don't be telling me it's KJV only if you got dust in your KJV Bible.
You understand what I'm saying?
Don't tell me well, it's this or that if you don't even read.
So what I'm trying to say is, listen,
Now, if you're redfaced and your neck is heated up, please understand
that the KJV was a new translation in 1611.
And I'm sure that people back then was thinking, man, this ain't right.
This is not the true word of God.
All I'm trying to say is I believe God is bigger than us.
And God can have his will and way no matter what.
I do, I like, and I, listen, this what we have tonight,
I have preached many, many, many, many, many.
I'm talking 100s of sermons out of this Bible.
It's a King James Version study Bible, but I also study, I have an ASM 95.
So listen, I don't know who that is for tonight.
Okay, but I just thought it was a good time because we're talking
about different words and different texts to share that.
Sometimes we get so legalistic that we that we actually
hinder what God wants to do in our life.
And so, Anyway, if you give a, if you give my
six-year-old a KJV, I'm going to take it out of her hands and give her an
NSB 95 or CSB or ESV.
You understand what I'm saying?
that's just what I'm going to do, okay?
And you can say, oh, well, she's not going to get it.
No, she'll get it.
So we're going to jump back to these 3 woes.
If you're with me, say I'm kind of with you.
Jumping right in.
So we're in Revelation.
Chapter 9.
So we're going to look at the 1st one tonight.
And we're going to read quite a few verses here because they
kind of expand on the description of these trumpets.
We've already talked about the 4th trumpet.
Now we're in the 5th trumpet, and this is what it says.
And the 5th angel sounded, and I saw
a star fall from heaven under the earth, onto the earth, sorry.
And to him was given the key of the bottomless pit.
And he opened the bottomless pit, and there arose a smoke out
of the pit as the smoke of a great furnace, and the sun in the air were
darkened by reason of the smoke of the pit.
There came out of the smoke locust upon the earth, and
unto them was given power, as the scorpions of the earth have power.
And it was commanded them that they should not hurt the
grass of the earth, neither any green thing, neither any tree, but
only those men which have not the seal of God in their foreheads.
And to them was given that they should not kill them, but
they should be tormented 5 months.
And their torment was that the as the torment of a scorpion
when he striketh a man.
And in those days shall man shall men seek death,
and he shall not find it, and shall desire to die, and death shall flee from them.
Could you imagine the torment here, the torture?
And the shapes of the locusts would like unto horses prepared in the
battle and on their heads, whereas it were crowns like gold
in their faces, whereas the faces of men, and they
had hair as the hair of women, and their teeth, whereas the teeth
of lions, and they had breastplates, as it were breastplates
of iron, and the sound of the wings was as the sound of chariots of many
horses running the battle.
They had tails like in the scorpions, and there were stings and their tails
and their power was to hurt men. 5 months.
Isn't that a scary verse, right?
Their power is to hurt men for 5 months.
And they had a king over them.
Which is the angel of the bottomless pit.
Whose name in the Hebrew tongue is Abaddon, but in the Greek tongue hath
his name Apollyon.
Now we can tell this is a very is quite different
in the 1st 4 trumpets.
We are now dealing with most likely the demonic realm.
There's a star that falls from heaven, most likely a fallen angel
that is given the keys to the bottomless pit.
He opens the abyss and outcomes, an army of
locusts with the power of scorpions and all the
description that we just read.
But here is the most, in my opinion, horrific detail.
They were directed to not go after the trees that
are grass or anything like that.
No, they are commanded to go straight to those who do
not have the seal of God on their foreheads.
Now, I read this as that means
everyone accept the 144,000 our
fair game for torment by the Army of Demonic Locust.
They cannot take life.
But only torture.
And this goes on for 5 months.
Now, you may be thinking that it's randomly used this concept of a scorpion's tail.
and sting here, and where we live, scorpions praise God are not very prevalent.
I mean, I guess they're around, but, you know, it's not like I'm squashing them around the house a lot.
You know what I'm saying?
But in the Middle East, however, especially in Bible times, they are a real threat.
So the reader would know exactly the danger that is being communicated here.
Now, these locusts have a king, and this king has a name.
Look again at verse 11.
They have a king as king over them, the angel of the abyss.
His name in Hebrew is Abaddon.
And in the Greek, his he has the name Apollyon.
Now, this is the only use of his name in scripture,
specifically the Greek rendering Apollyon.
This name literally means destroyer.
Now, although at times, this name is used for Satan.
There are some that read Revelation,
and there seems to be scripture that distinguishes the two.
For example, we hear about Satan in Revelation 20.
When he is in prison for the 1000 year reign, and he is literally
called, you know, Satan, he has the name there.
And so we see that this could be another
kind of like an underling of Satan himself
given power and authority
to rule this army.
But either way, he lives up to his name, destroyer.
Now, do I think that this army are literal locusts?
I personally do not.
Many have made speculations on modern things that
John wouldn't have seen and not been able to describe clearly today.
For example, is this a vision of helicopters?
I mean, there are people that think that,
Could this be another advanced tactical vehicle that would
not have been around them, but are now, is this a literal demonic army?
Is this a symbolic imagery that needs to be carefully
ironed out detail by detail?
And I hate to break it to you, but We cannot know for sure.
Just like a lot of revelation, there's simply you can speculate and speculate.
But we'll never know.
And I pray that we never do know.
But all we know is that this army of whatever it
is has the power and ability to torture those on the earth.
And what that tells me is, I
do not want anyone I know, or anyone that I
don't know, to have to go through that.
And so once again, may this create urgency
in our soul winning.
And I know that, listen, we're used to basically
most, I'm not going to say all because I'm
not God, so I don't have all the answers, but on Sunday morning, I try to
give as, I mean, we go, we go small little portions of
text so I can give as many answers as possible.
When we leave here, I want us to basically understand everything we
could possibly understand about those 3 words.
You know what I'm saying?
But here it's impossible.
All we know is that this is going to happen.
All we know is that there are going to be those who are tortured for 5 months.
All we know is that the only way out of this is Jesus.
And guess what?
Here's the thing.
There are people that believe that maybe we'll be here
when this time is coming and all I've got to say is this.
I just, when I look at scripture and I look at all the views.
I just believe that we're going to be delivered from the wrath to come.
And so I praise God for that.
But either way, I believe it's also going to get worse
before it gets even to this point.
And so as we see our world starting to bend
more and more towards the end, how
are we responding?
Are we so distracted that we don't care?
Are we are we in such a, are we trying to build
up our kingdoms here on earth that we get distracted
by the fact that Jesus, the king, is soon to return?
This world is going to be destroyed.
Everything we know in this world will come to
no longer exist, but praise God.
God is gonna make everything you.
And I'm going to be part of that new kingdom.
And so that's what I'm looking forward to.
So what opportunities are you taking tonight?
Are you letting your difficult circumstances or your success
or even your tragedy, whatever it is, distract you from the task at hand?
You know, it's beautiful.
We were at before we go, we're going to pray here in a second.
We were at the park.
Last night.
And it was an amazing scene because I
had to push river a little bit because I'm like, don't say hi to that girl.
She's like, no.
I said, you don't you don't get to say that.
Go say hi to that girl.
And she finally, you know, she was doing this thing when she was like walking
close to her and then she'd look away and then she'd
walk close to her again and she'd look away and I'm just like, like, you just, I was getting frustrated.
I said, just go say hi, make a friend.
And this girl found out her family is from Italy, like, straight up from Italy,
like, speaking Italian, right there in front of us.
I'm like, man, that's cool.
I don't know what you just said.
And so they start playing together and another
family from another ethnicity, another culture,
another race comes and they have a bunch of kids.
And so they're running up and I said, River Ridley, get them to come play too.
And so they're like, man, okay, all right.
Because once you kind of get your feet wet in it, it kind of becomes easier and easier.
And it was beautiful.
And you might think, what is this whole point?
By the end of the night, not only were
the kiddos playing together, I straight up went
Coach Mo, we played like Sharks and Minnows and the
floor is lava, like I was like screaming, go all the time.
It was it was great.
Literally one of the kids was like, I was like, hey, I got to go talk to the adults now.
They're like, no, coach, come back and coach us.
I was like, oh man.
But anyway, but not only were the kids playing and talking
with each other and doing all that.
But now the parents were talking with each other.
And I was able to talk about my faith and I was able to talk about the church
and I was to talk about Jesus.
And what I'm trying to say is all it took was
one little step of a child just to go and play with another child.
And it opened the door.
Guys, listen, we complicate soul winning too much.
You think, well, if I don't know everything, if I don't know this, but I don't know that.
What if they ask me a question that I don't have?
Guess what?
Tell them you don't know the answer.
Just tell them about Jesus.
Listen, if you don't know about Jesus, we didn't have a whole other conversation with you.
If you don't know the gospel.
If you don't know, if you can't tell someone what he has done for you and how you
were lost and now you're saved, we need to have a conversation with you, forget
everyone else, you need to become saved.
So what I'm trying to say is all this stuff is scary.
I get it.
But really, it's only scary if you look at it in the fact of we are so
apathetic towards those who are lost.
That should scare us.
into a heart that wants to see souls one.
So it has bound eyes closed all of his place.